<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon setting forth the duties of the Irish Protestants arising from the Irish Rebellion, 1641 and the Irish tyranny, 1688, &amp;c. : preached ... October 23. 1692 / by Edward, Lord Bishop of Cork and Ross.</title>
            <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65562</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22564</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12124819</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12124819</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54544</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65562)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54544)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 907:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon setting forth the duties of the Irish Protestants arising from the Irish Rebellion, 1641 and the Irish tyranny, 1688, &amp;c. : preached ... October 23. 1692 / by Edward, Lord Bishop of Cork and Ross.</title>
                  <author>Wettenhall, Edward, 1636-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Norman ;</publisher>
                  <publisher>By R. Roberts,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <pubPlace>Reprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd, I, 9-10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="order_to_preach">
            <pb facs="tcp:54544:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54544:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54544:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Thurſday,</hi> the <hi>13th.</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1692.</date> By the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, in Parliament Aſſembled.
<lb/>Ordered,</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THAT the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cork</hi> do Preach in <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> on the Twenty third Day of this Month of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> before the Lords of this Houſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Gerard Bor,</hi> Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Monday,</hi> the <hi>24th.</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1692.</date> By the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, in Parliament Aſſembled.
<lb/>Ordered,</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THAT the Thanks of this Houſe be given to the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cork,</hi> for his Sermon Preached yeſterday in <hi>Chriſt-Church:</hi> And that the Earl of <hi>Drogheda</hi> and the Lord Viſcount <hi>Bleſſinton</hi> do accordingly give the Thanks of this Houſe to the ſaid Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cork,</hi> and deſire him to cauſe his Sermon to be Printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Gerard Bor,</hi> Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54544:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Setting forth The Duties of the IRISH Proteſtants, Ariſing from The Iriſh Rebellion, 1641. AND The Iriſh Tyranny, 1688, &amp;c. Preached before His EXCELLENCY the LORD LIEUTENANT, AND THE Lords SPIRITUAL and TEMPORAL, And divers of the Commons: In <hi>CHRIST-CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH, D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN, October</hi> 23. 1692.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDWARD,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Cork</hi> and <hi>Roſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN:</hi> Printed for <hi>William Norman.</hi> Reprinted at <hi>London</hi> by R. <hi>Roberts.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="explanation_of_sigla">
            <pb facs="tcp:54544:3"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE Particular Service for the Day, according to the Order of the Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> being ſomewhat long, the Preacher was forced to contract his Sermon, by omitting in ſeveral places ſome parts thereof. But the Paſſages omitted in the Pulpit, are inſerted in the Print; yet ſo, as that what was omitted is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from what was delivered: If of any length, by being ſhut in thus, **[ ]**: <hi>If ſmaller, only thus, [ ].</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54544:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached <hi>October</hi> 23. 1692.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 COR. I. 9, 10.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We had the ſentence of death in our ſelves, that we ſhould not truſt in our ſelves, but in God which raiſeth the dead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who hath delivered us from ſo great a death, and doth deliver; in whom we truſt that he will yet deliver us.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F my <hi>Choice</hi> of theſe Words on this Occaſion, I hope there needs no other Account, than that it is more our Churches than mine.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Time</hi> when our Apoſtle and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in Tribulation, as well as Faith, had this <hi>ſentence of death in themſelves,</hi> was in the <hi>Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble which came unto them in Aſia, (verſ. 80)</hi> and this Hiſtory whereto this is ſuppoſed to refer, we have, <hi>Acts</hi> xix.</p>
            <p>The Honour of the <hi>great Goddeſs Diana, whom all Aſia and the World then worſhipped,</hi> and of <hi>the Image which fell down from Jupiter,</hi> had now received a deadly Wound: <hi>Her Temple</hi> was likely to be <hi>deſpiſed, and her Magnificence deſtroyed:</hi> for that <hi>This Paul had perſuaded and turn'd away the People, ſaying, That</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:54544:4"/> 
               <hi>they are no gods which are made with hands:</hi> A Peſtilent Doctrine indeed! For it had this effect at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> That <hi>Demetrius</hi>'s <hi>Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Shrines</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> They were [moſt probably] pretty Medals with <hi>Diana</hi>'s Image, and her Temples, upon them; much finer and more valuable than our Neighbours <hi>Agnus Det's),</hi> and ſuch like Trinkets, would not go off as they had done: <hi>The Craft by which the Silver-ſmith</hi> and his Fellow-Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>got their wealth,</hi> was in danger to be <hi>ſet at nought;</hi> and now 'twas time for the Craftsmen to act at leaſt the Zealots, to <hi>cry out two hours</hi> together, <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians,</hi> to <hi>raiſe no ſmall ſtir;</hi> to put <hi>the City in confuſion,</hi> and Countrey in an uproar; to <hi>lay hold on Paul's Companions,</hi> and him too, if they could catch him; and to <hi>ruſh with one accord into the Theatre,</hi> there to feed the Wild Beaſts with the Bodies of God's Saints, and their own eyes with the Spectacle of them torn in pieces and devoured. At this Juncture, <hi>We had,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>the ſentence of death in our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtory indeed matches not the Bloodineſs and Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of this Day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Greece</hi> was a Civiler Countrey, though bigotted enough by <hi>Prophets of their own,</hi> Poets and Lyars. One Wandring Jew, our Apoſtle, and a Couple of poor <hi>Macedonian</hi> Travellers, <hi>Gaius and Ariſtarchus, his Companions,</hi> would have ſatisfied the Fury of that Conflux of Idolaters from all the World, then at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> One thouſand two hundred eighty three perſons a day, for an hundred and twenty days together (or one with another) that is, <note n="*" place="margin">This is the Account in Sir <hi>John Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi>'s Book; and as it was given in to the Parliament in <hi>England.</hi> But if from <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 23. on which Morning the Rebellion broke (out, we reckon to <hi>March</hi> 1. which is ſomewhat more exact there were 9 days above the four Calendar Months, that is 129 days. And then there fell only, one day with another, 1193 Perſons a day, and 103 over in the whole.</note> 
               <hi>An hundred fifty four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Souls, Men, Women, and Children, in four Months time,</hi> as the Account was given in by the Actors themſelves, leſt they ſhould have been thought to have been more bloody than they were, was a Sacrifice which none but <hi>Iriſh</hi> Prieſts and <hi>Popiſh</hi> Votaries could ever have thought of, or attempted.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:54544:4"/>
            <p>Nay, <hi>Diana</hi>'s Prieſts in the <hi>Acts,</hi> were yet more reaſonable than we think of: For their People having got two Perſons to make an Example of, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> verſ. 31. <hi>Certain of the Aſiatic Prieſts,</hi> (ſuch in all likelihood they were) ſtood ſo much <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Friends,</hi> as to preſerve even him, though Principal, from the Theatre, and being there a real Tragedy. Admit then the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Prieſts in a certain Sacrifice to be no Idolaters, yet in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Sacrifices they have far exceeded all the Idolaters in the World.</p>
            <p>But however the Hiſtory will not in all circumſtances come up to our Caſe; the Habit of Mind, or Temper here avowed by the Apoſtle in himſelf and Brethren, will be moſt ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and intimately becoming all, whoſe Condition at any time may have anſwered theirs, by having had a Sentence of Death in themſelves.</p>
            <p>We will therefore view, Firſt, Their outward Condition, and God's Deſign upon them thereby, <hi>(verſ.</hi> 9.) Then the Faith our Apoſtle avows, <hi>(verſ. 10.)</hi> which are the main Conſiderables in theſe two Verſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>We had a ſentence of death in our ſelves:</hi> That was their Condition. <hi>That we ſhould not truſt in our ſelves, but in God which raiſeth the dead:</hi> That was God's Deſign upon them and us.—God in his Providence many times ſees fit to bring his faithfulleſt Servants into ſuch Plunges of Miſery and Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, whence none but an Almighty Unſeen Power can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve them; and this, to the end he may teach them, and others by them, dependance on himſelf alone. They are ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, as that they muſt truſt to Inviſible Omnipotence or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; as in the Text, <hi>To God that raiſeth the dead:</hi> For their Condition is in effect ſuch as that of men in the Grave, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power of Death.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He avows, <hi>God had delivered,</hi> and even ſtill to the inſtant in which he ſpoke, <hi>did deliver,</hi> and that they <hi>truſted he would yet deliver them.</hi>—When in Deplorable or Deſperate Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, by an Almighty Hand people have been delivered, they ought, into whatſoever Condition they ſhall thereafter be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54544:5"/> reduced, for ever to truſt to that Deliverer. However low the Faith of any other perſons at any time may run without ſin, the leaſt Diffidence in thoſe who have been thus Delivered, is high Ingratitude.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Obſervations are the proper Reſult of the Words, as far as from a ſingular Inſtance any general Rules can be drawn; and the Conſequence of both is ſo ſtrict, that neither much need a further proof: I ſhall therefore but touch on what I had prepared.</p>
            <p>And the firſt being <hi>Matter of Fact,</hi> through ſeveral long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Ages, the propereſt proof of it would be <hi>Hiſtorical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords,</hi> both as to Particular Perſons, and that great Publick Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the Church.</p>
            <p>**[As to particular perſons. The Holy Ghoſt ſingling out ſome of the moſt Faithful men, and greateſt Favourites of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, under the Old Teſtament, names eſpecially three, who were in their days Wonders of Danger and Miſery, and yet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained as wondrous Deliverance, through the Faith which they learn'd and practis'd in their moſt deſperate Circumſtances: The Three were <hi>Noah, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Job, Ezek.</hi> xiv. 14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Lives of each of theſe are ſo many Exemplifications or Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of the Caſe before us.</p>
            <p>What could <hi>Noah</hi> truſt to, or whence could he hope for (ſhall I ſay, or imagine) any help poſſible, but from a Power ſuperior to Earth and Air, (from him that dwelleth in Heaven) when he ſaw <hi>the Fountains of the great deep broken up, and the windows of heaven opened,</hi> and continued mighty <hi>rains for forty days and forty nights?</hi> As far as fleſh and blood can ſee, he <hi>had a ſentence of death in himſelf;</hi> at leaſt could truſt in nothing but the Living God, to ſurvive that Flood by which all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, except himſelf and his, periſhed: And according to the Growth of his Dangers, no doubt was that of his Faith. By Dreadful Diſcipline he proceeded from Faith to Faith. <hi>By faith,</hi> faith the Author to the <hi>Hebrews, Noah prepared an Ark for the ſaving his houſe.</hi> And by that Faith continued, and advancing ſtill, may I ſay, he ſaved both the Ark, himſelf, and all with him
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54544:5"/> in it. For no more could he, and his, have lived in the Ark without a kind of Miracle of Faith, than the ark in ſuch a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge, without a Miracle of Power.</p>
            <p>Again, What could <hi>Daniel</hi> truſt to in the Den of Lions, by Nature and Hunger mercileſs? What Power below God's, that made them, could have changed their Natures, or <hi>ſent an Angel to have ſhut their mouths?</hi> But, <hi>through faith,</hi> ſaith the now mentioned Author; <hi>He ſtopped the mouths of Lions,</hi> Heb. xi. 33. <hi>He was taken out of the Den, and no manner of hurt was found upon him, becauſe he believed upon his God,</hi> ſaith he himſelf, <hi>Dan.</hi> vi. 23.</p>
            <p>Further: What could <hi>Job</hi> truſt to, when beſides his being, from the heighth of Wealth and Plenty, reduc'd to Nakedneſs and Nothing; beſides his being bereaved of his Children in an inſtant, and no Relation left him, but one who ſeems to have ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the Devil againſt him; forſaken too of all Friends, ſave thoſe <hi>Miſerable Comforters,</hi> who with one mouth told him the cauſe of all his Miſery was his Hypocriſie; when beſides ſuch unheard-of, and united Calamities, his very Body was <hi>ſmitten with ſore boils, from the ſole of his foot to the crown of his head;</hi> and he <hi>ſitting down among the aſhes, took a Potſherd to ſcrape him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf withal:</hi> What could this Mirror, ſhall I ſay, or Miracle of Conſtancy and Patience, have recourſe to, but <hi>him that kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and maketh alive; him that bringeth down to the grave, and bringeth up?</hi> And to him he reſolutely applies, <hi>Chap.</hi> xiii. 15. <hi>Though he ſlay me, yet will I truſt in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Great <hi>Triumvirate,</hi> we will only add the <hi>Man after God's own heart;</hi> Into what frequent Gulphs of Miſery was he caſt? <hi>The waters came in unto his very ſoul; he ſunk in the deep mire, where there was no ſtanding; and in the deep waters, where the flouds overflowed him; He was weary with his crying, and his eyes failed him while he waited on God,</hi> Pſal. lxix. 1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet <hi>on God he waited,</hi> verſ. 3. And, <hi>At what time I am afraid, I will truſt in God.</hi> Pſal. lvi. 3.</p>
            <p>Finally, This has been all along verified, not only in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Saints, but in the great body of them, the Church. For brevity ſake, let one Inſtance thereof ſuffice.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:54544:6"/>
            <p>God had plac'd the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> his then only viſible Church, in the beſt part of <hi>Egypt,</hi> in <hi>Goſhen;</hi> under the happy Government, at leaſt prime Miniſtry, of their Brother <hi>Joſeph:</hi> He could here have made them a numerous, and moſt Flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing People; But this would not have brought them to the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of his Works, nor Dependance on his Power. They muſt therefore firſt be brought into Bondage, <hi>in Mortar, Brick, and all manner of ſervice,</hi> (even to make <hi>Brick without Straw) under Taskmaſters which made them ſerve with Rigour.</hi> Their <hi>Male-Children</hi> muſt be decreed to the <hi>River,</hi> caſt therein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and deſtroy'd; inſomuch that they <hi>muſt groan by reaſon of their Bondage.</hi> In this Condition they learn <hi>to cry unto the Lord,</hi> the God of their Fathers; and <hi>their cry came up unto him,</hi> Exod. ii. 23. But even yet they are not by ſufficient Miſery ripe for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance. <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and the <hi>Hoſt of the Egyptians,</hi> muſt be Arm'd, <hi>all the Horſes, and Horſemen, and Chariots of Egypt muſt be drawn out</hi> againſt them, and in purſuit overtake them: They muſt be <hi>ſhut up in the wilderneſs, in the Straits of Pihahiroth, with the ſea before, and their enemies behind:</hi> And now they muſt <hi>ſtand ſtill, and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord,</hi> that they may learn, <hi>It is the Lord that fights for them,</hi> and from <note place="margin">Exod. xiv. 9, 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> him alone cometh their help. But they did not all learn this, and therefore the <hi>Carcaſſes of them that believed not, fell in the wilderneſs,</hi> (though neither by <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> nor in the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> leſt their Enemies ſhould triumph.) Thoſe few who did believe, <hi>recieved the promiſe,</hi> and were led into the Promiſed Reſt, by that Mighty Arm which brought them out of their Bondage.</p>
            <p>By theſe Perſonal Inſtances of <hi>Noah, Daniel, Job</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> Saints undoubtedly of the firſt Magnitude, and by the National Caſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the People whom God had choſen to himſelf out of all People; it appears, as to the matter of Fact, That God often reduces his faithfulleſt and moſt beloved Servants to ſuch critical depths of Miſery, whence none but an Almighty hand can retrieve them; and wherein they muſt either truſt in him, or give up all Truſt, and be loſt.]**</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54544:6"/>
            <p>But why ſhould God make any Peoples Courſe of Life ſo uneven? And why ſuch Peoples eſpecially?</p>
            <p>In Anſwer hereto: Though we, who in our Delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Conſults, ſcarce many times know what it is, which moſt ſways, and laſtly determines us to a Reſolution, may not preſume to ſay, where God has not ſaid it firſt, This or that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved God thus to Act; yet with humble Reverence we may ſay in general, He does it undoubtedly for moſt holy and wiſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Government of the World. The Particulars we ſhall fully know at the day of the revelation of all things. Mean while, As in <hi>Giving Rain and fruitful Seaſons,</hi> and thereby <hi>fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling our hearts with food and gladneſs;</hi> ſo ſometimes in changing his hand and ſundry wiſe giving us <hi>a Sentence of death in our ſelves,</hi> whence yet, as he ſees fit, he grants Reprieves: In all theſe he <hi>leaves not himſelf without a Witneſs.</hi> Did all Humane Affairs move in one conſtant, even regular ſort, as fixed Stars in an Orb, whither no Clouds or Storms ariſe, ſome would ſay, <hi>It is good for us to be here,</hi> and never think of another World, or of True Happineſs: Others perhaps would cry out, All things come to paſs of courſe; There's no ſuch thing as Providence. Now, that we ſee ſuch Eccentrical Motions and Epicycles, we muſt acknowledge there is an hand that agitates, governs and over rules the whole Frame: And thoſe who demand Miracles, that they may believe, may find them in and upon themſelves, in that they, among others, are now alive.</p>
            <p>But it will be ſaid, The Faithful need not theſe Teſtimonies; for according to the Hypotheſis, they are already Faithful. True: they need them not to beget the firſt Faith, but they need them to quicken and confirm the Faith they have.</p>
            <p>But ſtill that part of the Challenge recurs, Why ſhould God pitch upon his moſt faithful Servants thus to exerciſe? It ſeems fitter ſuch Examples ſhould be made on thoſe, who have more deſerved ſuch Severities.</p>
            <p>The Anſwer may be, Wicked men in ſuch Difficulties would not truſt in God, apply to Him, or glorifie Him at all: They would rather turn impatient and deſperate. Let <hi>Saul</hi> be at a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54544:7"/> loſs, and he'll ſeek to the next Witch or Devil, inſtead of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting all to God. And thoſe in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> on whom ſome of the <hi>laſt Plagues</hi> came, <hi>gnawed their tongues for pain, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed the God of Heaven, but repented not of their deeds to give him glory,</hi> Rev. xvi. 9, 10, 11. Wherefore to ſuch who exerciſe no Faith, who apply not to God, or acknowledge Him, there is moſt juſtly no Deliverance: Out of one Miſery they fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another; out of a Temporal, into an Eternal Abyſs.</p>
            <p>But when Holy Men ſuffer, yet ſuffering ſubmit with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to God's hand, call upon Him <hi>out of the deep,</hi> and in the Deep ſtill truſt in him, and are delivered, God is glorified eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way: His Almighty Power and Veracity is glorified in their Deliverance; and the power of his Grace in them, is glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their adheſion to him, and dependance upon him, even while he delayed to deliver, and ſeemed not to ſuccour them. The Devil and wicked men muſt ſee and acknowledge to their own confuſion, God has ſuch Children, who though he frown and chaſtiſe. [though he let looſe wicked Men, and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Spirits upon them, which may vex them till they are tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Curſe God and die]</hi> yet they will ſtill hold faſt good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, truſt their God, love him, and wait his time. They <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> and therefore <hi>will not make haſte;</hi> will not by impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence put that God out of his own Methods, who has delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them from ſo great a death, and doth deliver them, [even at the very <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or inſtant of their greateſt oppreſſion and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, in that under that very anguiſh they ſubſiſt] and in <hi>whom they truſt, that he will yet deliver them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence we deduced our ſecond Note; That when by an Almighty hand people have been delivered from the Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of Danger, into whatever Difficulties they ſhall after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be brought, they ought for ever to truſt to that Deliverer.</p>
            <p>** [For ſuch Perſons have the ſame Reaſons in common with others to truſt God, and they have beſides Perſonal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons peculiar to themſelves.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reaſons</hi> which Chriſtian people <hi>in common</hi> have to truſt God, are his infinite <hi>Power, Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> by which he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54544:7"/> ſeems as it were in Honour bound to provide for, and preſerve, whom he has put into being and dependance upon Him, while they own this dependance, begging and truſting to Him, that by his Viſitation He will preſerve the Spirit which He gave: And beſides all this, His Word and Promiſe ſo to do. Theſe Conſiderations make it <hi>Injuſtice</hi> in any who Know God, to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt Him.</p>
            <p>But beſides theſe common Motives, ſuch Perſons whom God has more Signally Deliver'd have had experience of his Loving-Kindneſs and Good Will, <hi>Particularly</hi> to themſelves; and this laſt, is all that Chriſtians may, or that perhaps moſt of them are apt to doubt, That God is Able enough, and Wiſe enough to help us, none (who believe the Being of a God) can queſtion; But whether He Will or no, by reaſon of our guilt, is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be doubted. Now ſuch Perſons having had experience of God's good Will in particular to them, as well as of his Power, Wiſdom, Veracity and Goodneſs in general, are more exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſinful, if Diffident. This makes it in them <hi>Ingratitude</hi> to Diſtruſt Him.] **</p>
            <p>But is it then the Duty of all Chriſtian People, when in Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſimply to truſt in God for Deliverance? Or is it not truly ſaid, That Truſt in God for ſuch Particular Mercies as we want, is not (like Repentance, and the Faith of Aſſent, and ſome like Particulars) abſolutely every Mans Duty who hears thereof, but the Duty only of ſome who are qualify'd; and of them to, with certain Cautions, and under certain Conditions?</p>
            <p>The Anſwer ſhall be very brief, plain, and diſtinct, in Four Concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Particular Truſt in God, being required to be proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to God's Promiſes, and there being nothing that the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful can want, which God has not promiſed, there is nothing that they can want which they may not truſt to Him for: <hi>The young Lions do lack and ſuffer hunger, but they that fear the Lord ſhall not want any good thing:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. xxxiv. 9, 10.</note> Only we muſt be careful, our Confidence take in all the Promiſe; That is,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:54544:8"/>2. They who would acceptably, or according to the will of God, truſt in Him; muſt take heed they be not without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward qualifications which bring Men. within the compaſs of the Promiſe. The Promiſe is to ſuch who fear the Lord; not to them who lightly eſteem Him. And again, <hi>Every Man,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>who hath this hope in him, purifieth himſelf even as He is pure,</hi> 1 John iii. 3. There is nothing more deplorable than to hear looſe, impenitent, carnal Perſons (by Carnal, I mean ſuch who are without a ſenſe of Godlineſs, or Religion, upon their Hearts) ſay upon every Exigent, <hi>I truſt in God:</hi> you truſt in God! What have you to do to truſt in Him? Hear what God faith to you, <hi>What haſt thou to do—that thou ſhouldeſt take my Covenant in thy Mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt Inſtruction, and caſieſt my words behind thee,</hi> Pſal. l. 16, 17. <hi>Cleanſe your Hands, ye Sinners, and purifie your Hearts, ye Double minded;</hi> and then <hi>draw nigh to God, and He will draw nigh to you,</hi> James iv. 8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe God has no otherwiſe promiſed particular outward Bleſſings to us, than as He ſees them good for us <hi>(They that fear the Lord ſhall want nothing that is good)</hi> In our truſt to God for ſuch things, we muſt always intermix ſubmiſſion to his Wiſdom and Will. We need not doubt but He will certainly give the outward Goods we would have, if He ſees us fit for them; and there is nothing fits us more, than Purity, or Univerſal Holineſs, which we urged in the former Particular; and Humility, or perfect Submiſſion to God, which we preſs in this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Inaſmuch as God is without Variableneſs, or Shadow of Changing, conſtant unto Himſelf, and works not extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily but upon extraordinary occaſions, inaſmuch as he alters not the Courſe of Nature by the uſual Acts of his Providence, but Nature and Providence ſweetly agree; they therefore, who truſt in God to any Particular Purpoſe, muſt with ſuch Holineſs and Submiſſion as directed, mix Diligence and the uſe of Means proper, in order to their End. He was, it's true, no very good Man, in whom I am about to inſtance; but in this point he ſeems to have been very Exemplary, for a right Procedure in his truſting in God, <hi>When Joab ſaw that the Front of the Battle was</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:54544:8"/> 
               <hi>againſt him, before and behind, he choſe of the choice Men of Iſrael, and put them in Array againſt the Syrians. And the reſt of he People he deliver'd into the hand of Abiſhai his Brother, that he might put them in Array againſt the Children of Ammon. And he ſaid, If the Syrians be too ſtrong for me, then thou ſhalt help me: And if the Children of Ammon be too ſtrong for thee, than I will come and help thee. Be of good Courage, and let us play the Men, for our People, and for the Cities of our God: And the Lord do that which ſeemeth good to Him,</hi> 2 Sam. x. 9, 10, 11, 12. Here's a Man now, ſuppoſing him otherwiſe Vertuous, that truſts for Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from his Enemies, as he ought to do. He uſes all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and all the Courage he could, and then like a Brave Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, calmly ſubmits the iſſue to God.</p>
            <p>Prayer, in the Name of Chriſt Jeſus, for the obtaining what we truſt to God for, is but an act of true Chriſtian Truſt, or as I may ſay, the Venting of it; and therefore I ſay nothing particularly touching it: But ſuppoſing all the Conditions before ſet down (namely, That our Truſt grounds it ſelf upon God's Promiſe, That we honeſtly endeavour the Inward State and Temper required by the Promiſe, That we truſt for Outward Bleſſings with Submiſſion to God's Will, and that we be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in the uſe of Means proper to the deſigned Benefits, and particularly of Prayer) ſuppoſing, I ſay, theſe things obſerved, the Rule is, <hi>Truſt in Him at all times, O ye People; pour out your Hearts before Him: God is a Refuge for us.</hi> On theſe terms to truſt in God at all times, is our Duty as well as Intereſt.</p>
            <p>** [And for us, who have been Delivered in ſuch ſort as both our ſelves and Predeceſſors have been, not to truſt in our Deliverer; would be the vileſt Ingratitude as well as injuſtice—He has delivered us from ſo great a Death, (from all the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of our Enemies) He does ſtill Deliver us (from their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Malice:) Would it not now be the moſt abominable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quital, not to truſt Him, that He will yet Deliver us (from all their Machinations] **</p>
            <p>I am yet obliged by the Duty I owe the Day, and this Great Audience, to a more Particular Application: And I beſeech
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54544:9"/> You to continue Your Patience, on this more than common Occaſion, a little ſpace.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, As to matter of <hi>Particular Self-Reflection—We have had a Sentence of Death in our ſelves.</hi> This matter of Fact, as to our ſelves, I preſume we are ſenſible is true.—<hi>That we ſhould not truſt in our ſelves, but in God which raiſeth the Dead:</hi> That this was God's Deſign upon as many of us, as He ſaw Faithful Adherents to Him, we have ſeen to be no leſs certain. The only Queſtion is, Whether this Deſign have taken effect? Whether we, by our Dangers and Miſeries, have learn'd to lay aſide Carnal Refuges and Confidence, and duely <hi>to truſt in Him that. raiſeth the Dead.</hi> To go over the Particulars.</p>
            <p>We have had, I ſay, <hi>A Sentence of Death in our ſelves.</hi> WE, that is, our Anceſtors and Predeceſſors, this time was One and Fifty Years; and as many of us in our own Perſons, as were then of Judgment. It was then, inſtead of a Confeſſion, the Remorſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Beaſts of a Principal Conſpirator, when apprehended, That <hi>their Deſign was ſo far Advanced by that time, as it was not poſſible for Wit of Man to prevent it.</hi> So proud of themſelves, of their own Wiſdom, Counſels and Strength, ſo arrogant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, ſo contemptuous and implacable againſt us, was (I wiſh I could not ſay, is) the Malice of the Iriſh Papiſts, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of their Prieſts, who then had (God grant they ſtill have not) Charm'd that People out of all Reaſon and Bowels. And truly all who then judged as men do, might juſtly have been of the Conſpirators minds. For the Iriſh had the generality of the Caſtles, Forts, Sea-Ports and ſtrong Holds of the Kingdom in their Poſſeſſion. <hi>England</hi> was then as good as in Blood by their <hi>Arts,</hi> and ſo unable to help us; the <hi>Scots</hi> ſome while abuſed into a Neutrality; and Foreign Countries ready to pour in Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours to them. So that moſt reaſonably, in Forty One, had our Parents, Brethren, or We in our own Perſons, <hi>a Sentence of Death in our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, WE lately, in the End of Eighty Eight, and in the years—89 and 90, (a <hi>Second-Rebellion</hi> in little more than <hi>Half an Age;</hi> which yet if any will not allow to be another
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54544:9"/> 
               <hi>Iriſh Rebellion,</hi> we will, to gratifie them, at preſent ſtyle <hi>The Iriſh Tyranny;</hi> and perhaps more properly, for that Tyrants chooſe Methods of ſlow and lingring Murthers, <hi>Sentiat ſe Mori)</hi> We, I ſay, who were in this Kingdom during thoſe years, had really a <hi>Sentence of Death in our ſelves.</hi> For we knew our ſelves in the hands of Bloody Enemies; Enemies by Nation, Manners, Religion, and Intereſt; Enemies Inſolent, (and ſome few ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) Barbarous and Brutiſh; Enemies who never yet kept Faith, nor can it be preſumed ever will. We were Naked even as to Defenſive Weapon; Deprived of all manner of Refuge or Security; yea, many of us, often-times of the very Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Life. We were moſt cauſeleſly either under Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Reſtraints: and not ſeldom drawn out, and ſet forth as Men appointed for immediate Death. Our Surrounding Guards (not long before our Servants) ſtanding ready with their Arms, and calling for, <hi>The Word, The Word;</hi> and ſometimes the Commander in Chief Damning himſelf, that upon the firſt ſight of the Enemy, <hi>he would ſacrifice all our Heretick Souls to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</hi> Thus ſtood it with many of us, who are thought to have fared beſt. Others, and thoſe not a few, in ſeveral Places were under Formal Sentence of Death; Gallows and Executioners prepared and appearing. It was worſe yet with thoſe Forlorn Numbers driven before the Walls of <hi>DERRY,</hi> of whom God alone knows how many periſhed. And even thoſe Brave Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple within <hi>DERRY,</hi> and their Immortal Brethren of <hi>ENNIS-KILLIN,</hi> cannot but be eſteem'd, with our Apoſtle, <hi>to have been preſſed out of meaſure, above ſtrength, inſomuch as oftentimes to have deſpaired of Life;</hi> only reſolving in thoſe deſperate Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, to fall into the Hands of God, and not of Men; not to ſell Life with Diſhonour, or to be made the Scorn of Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners and Faithleſs Men. Theſe things are ſo manifeſt, that to uſe the words of our <hi>Town Clark</hi> in the <hi>Acts, They cannot be ſpoken againſt.</hi> It admits not Contradiction that we of late had a Sentence of Death in our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Now as to the Point Queſtionable, and to be Examin'd. Has this Sentence of Death, according to God's Deſign thereby
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54544:10"/> brought all of us, either us of <hi>Forty One,</hi> or us of <hi>Eighty Eight,</hi> off from our Carnal Refuges, and Carnal Life or Senſe of things? Do we now <hi>not truſt in our ſelves, but in God which raiſeth the Dead?</hi> Are we all of us, as Men ought to be, who have had ſo long the Sentence of Death in themſelves, prepared for Death? Have we in good earneſt perſwaded our ſelves, that God will raiſe the Dead; Ay, and bring them to Judgment too? Are we reſolved to live as Men only Reprieved a while? For our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is at beſt no better. We are perhaps delivered from a violent Death; but tomorrow or next day; (at leaſt we know not how ſoon) may we dye a Natural one. <hi>Behold</hi> (as <note place="margin">Gen. xxvii. 2.</note> good old <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſaid) <hi>I know not the Day of my Death.</hi> Now are we ready, Brethren? Has this Sentence of Death men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us? Can we each look up to Heaven, and ſay <hi>I truſt in God that raiſeth the Dead?</hi> If ſo, ſuch Mens Miſeries have made them Happy. But God knows, if we may judge by what appears to Humane Eyes, by the Face of things, by Peoples Manners, Talk, Habits, Air, and like Symptoms, the generality of us are as lewd, carnal, worldly, proud, vain and fantaſtick as ever. Some, I will hope, remember the Vows of their Miſery, and will never forget them: And to ſuch mainly belongs The ſecond part of my Application, the Exhortation and Advice following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God has deliver'd you from ſo great a Death: He does Deliver:</hi> Wherefore <hi>truſt to Him that He will yet Deliver you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. He has Delivered.</p>
            <p>'Twas His Hand, and His alone, in the <hi>Iriſh Rebellion;</hi> which that any Proteſtants did, or do here ſurvive, is little leſs then a Miracle. The Nation was Confederate, and as one Man againſt us. They had every where prepared the Inſtruments of Death, of all ſorts; and they as barbarouſly divers Months employed them; even till glutted with Blood, if Engliſh Blood could have glutted them. That they left us a Remnant, was God's over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Act, not at all their Intent or Will. Their Deſign, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, and diligent Endeavour was, to have cut off Root and Branch, <hi>the Mother with the Child:</hi> And leaſt our Aſhes ſhould have been a kind of a new Seedneſs of Proteſtants to the Land, they had forbid us ſo much as Burial.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:54544:10"/>
            <p>Again, 'Twas God's Hand, and His alone, that in the <hi>Iriſh Tyranny</hi> deliver'd us the Poſterity, Brethren, or Succeſſors of thoſe who fell in the <hi>Iriſh Rebellion.</hi> Their Prieſts indeed are ſaid this time not to have given ſuch Bloody Inſtructions as in the former day. Alas good Natur'd Men! They only at high Maſs (that is at their moſt ſacred Office, and in the higheſt pitch of their Charity) bid all their People Arm, at leaſt with Ruppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Bagonets pretty innocent Weapons!) and what other Arms they could get. They only interdicted them, under pain of Suſpenſion from Maſs, to be ſeen again after ſuch a ſhort day, unarm'd. Their Orders for Action only were, Plunder and Strip all Proteſtants, ſpoil and burn what you cannot poſſeſs; but ſpare Blood. That is, Kill not the Proteſtants, but ſtarve them with Cold and Hunger. O Merciful Prieſts! <hi>Quid reſert, ferro pereamne ruina</hi> But even this their Mercy laſted not long: When many of our Brethren had ſaved themſelves by timely retiring out of the Kingdom, how frequent Conſults were held, to have put to Death us the poor Remainder? And herein the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papal Clergy were conſtant and importunate to this bloody purpoſe, and their People (no doubt too many of themſelves) as ready for acting it. Now how a Clergy, and a head ſtrong, blind, abuſed Nation, who denyed even to <hi>their own King,</hi> as they call'd him, his Power, as often as he would uſe it in favour of Proteſtants; how, I ſay, both theſe came to be reſtrain'd from executing their own Will, we to this hour are at a loſs. It was not, as ſome have thought, a care of Preſerving the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks, which ſwayed them; for they had no regard to them, and thoſe of them whom they had in their Army or Councils, they ſcorned, hated, and to their power turn'd out of Place, little otherwiſe than they did Engliſh Proteſtants. It was not fear of an After-Reckoning: For by this means only they accounted they would have prevented all After-claps. Some times I have thought it was our Paucity: They ſcorned us, and eſteemed us too Few, conſidering their own Numbers, for them to ſacrifice. And really upon After thoughts herein, I believe thoſe, who left the Kingdom, did a Publick Service: For had the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54544:11"/> whole Body of the Engliſh ſtayed, ſo that our Number had made us Formidable, I queſtion not but there had been a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond General Maſſacre: Which what prevented, as to us, who were in their hands; eſpecially at that Critical Point of Time, when our Bleſſed Deliverer, and their Conqueror, appeared; cannot, as far as I am able to ſee, be aſſigned; except we ſay, It was God's Almighty Hand. He diſheartned them, and as in the caſe of thoſe Cities, through which <hi>Jacob</hi> and his Family journeyed <hi>(Gen. xxxv. 5.) The Terrour of God was upon them.</hi> He perfectly amuſed them, ſo that their <hi>Men of Might found not their Hands,</hi> nor their Wiſe Men their Counſels. <hi>He</hi> (then) <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us from ſo great a Death.</hi> And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He doth Deliver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How we have ſubſiſted, even ſince the Reduction, eſpecially in the Country, where for the moſt part both Towns and Fields were in a manner totally deſolate and waſte; where Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Stock, and, in many places, even Trees and Hedges, were deſtroyed; ſo that we might have rationally deſpaired of Food and Shelter; is to me next door to a Miracle. But when the Buſh burns, and burns, and continues ſtill burning, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes not, 'tis plain God is in it. <hi>He doth Deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us therefore <hi>truſt in Him that He will yet Deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis ſure, only the Power of our Enemies is abated, not their Malice or bloody Minds; I may add moſt juſtly, not their Pride or Expectations. Their very common People ſtick not to our face to tell us, <hi>They will yet have a Day for it;</hi> and they are as confident of an Army from <hi>France,</hi> as ever they were. It vexes, no doubt, the conſiderative part of their whole Nation, that they ſhould have been able from the Rebellion in <hi>Forty One,</hi> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a War of Twelve Years, and yet that this much more an Univerſal Effort of their whole Nation to have ſhaken off for ever the Engliſh Yoak, of which they had ſuch aſſurance, ſhould be fruitleſly over in ſo few years. They are therefore without queſtion buſie to retrieve our Confuſions; and that, amongſt themſelves, with their uſual Confidence. But let our Confidence be <hi>in God that raiſeth the Dead,</hi> from whence in a figure we have been raiſed.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:54544:11"/>
            <p>Only let us remember, truſting in God is, as ſaid, a kind of conditionate Duty; and we muſt take care, firſt, that we be duly qualified to truſt in God for the Deliverance we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: Secondly, that we do not contravene, or in our Actions contradict ſuch Truſt.</p>
            <p>For our being duly qualified to truſt in God in any reſpect, we have heard we muſt <hi>cleanſe our Heaats;</hi> repent of all known, or even by us ſuſpected Evils, allowing our ſelves in neigher: <hi>If our Hearts condemn us not, then have we confidence towards God,</hi> 1 John iii. 21.</p>
            <p>And particularly for qualifying our ſelves to truſt in God for Deliverance ſtill from our <hi>Iriſh</hi> Enemies, we muſt take care we repent of, and live not in thoſe Sins for which we may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally conclude God gave us of late into Subjection and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion under them. I will not enter into particular Mens par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Sins; I leave that to their own Conſciences, which will eaſily tell them, <hi>Such and ſuch a Sin has God viſited upon me and mine.</hi> Inſtead of that attempt, I will only touch ſuch publick Sins which were open and bare-fac'd amongſt us; and not all of them neither, for time will not permit. As principal ones then, I muſt tax,</p>
            <p>1. A curſed Conjunction of <hi>Worldlineſs, Senſuality</hi> and <hi>Haughtineſs,</hi> with <hi>meer Formality in Religion;</hi> moſt of us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting our ſelves with the Name of Reformed, without any real practical Reformation, or Zeal for promoting it. We were intent on getting Eſtates, on raiſing Families, on living in Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, on having all ſtoop to us; and we in heart regarded not him that had ſet us up, and both put, and ſo long kept our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies under our Feet. In plain terms, had we Proteſtants been as induſtrious, firſt, our ſelves to have lived according to the Truth and Power of the Reformed Religion, and then to have inſtructed the <hi>Iriſh</hi> therein, as we were to ſecure our ſelves the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Lands; had we been as careful to make them knowing good Chriſtians, as our ſelves rich and great; we had, in all probability, never ſeen the Rebellion of <hi>Forty One,</hi> nor the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of the late <hi>Eighty Eight,</hi> and following years. I muſt but name things.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:54544:12"/>
            <p>I tax [2] Frequent <hi>Oppreſſion of,</hi> or Squeezing, <hi>our poor Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> and making our <hi>Engliſh Tenants Vaſſals.</hi> Many of us, to this day, much more affect and court the Iriſh, than our own Countrey-men; and will theſe at any time for Twenty Shillings a year: I ſay nothing of the Imprudence herein, and Publick Detriment hereby; But ſuch Landlords ſure remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not, that though we ought <hi>to do good unto all, yet eſpecially to thoſe who are of the Houſhold of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot forbear, Laſtly to tax the <hi>Notorious Exceſs of all De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees</hi> in their <hi>Habit, Tables, Furniture</hi> and <hi>Equipage,</hi> conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Rank of each. We have been, many of us, reproach'd for this, of late, in <hi>England;</hi> yet we are at it again, as faſt as may be. Theſe and the like Evils we muſt repent of, and take care we return not to, if we would be qualified to truſt in God that he will yet Deliver us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As we muſt be qualified for ſuch Truſt, ſo if we would, that our Truſt for Deliverance from <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts ſhould be ſucceſsful, we muſt beware we do not practically contradict that Truſt. Now that All do.</p>
            <p>1. Who <hi>mixt with them,</hi> either in <hi>Sin, Society, Blood,</hi> or <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe who mix with them in <hi>Sin,</hi> muſt expect to be Sharers in their Vengeance, and to periſh one day With them; therefore By them, at leaſt by ſuch Mixture.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who mix with them in <hi>Society,</hi> will ſoon mix with them in ſin; and in its fore mentioned Conſequents, Vengeance and Ruine.</p>
            <p>Thoſe, who mix with them in <hi>Blood,</hi> are thereby moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately mixt in Society, and conſequently cannot avoid mixture in Sin. Nor is there any Probability, but that ſuch ſhould eſpecially mix with them in <hi>Religion;</hi> at leaſt, if they themſelves do not, the Poſterity of ſuch will. For in all ſuch Compoſitions, the Production does uſually <hi>Sequi Deteriorem partem;</hi> partake moſt ſtrongly of the III Leaven.</p>
            <p>2. It is another Practical Inconſiſtance in this Caſe, to <hi>Truſt God,</hi> that <hi>He ſhould deliver us</hi> from our <hi>Iriſh</hi> Popiſh Enemies;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54544:12"/> and yet to <hi>Truſt Them,</hi> 'Tis very true, we ought to be ſuch good Chriſtians as to keep Faith with them, (and God forbid we ſhould do otherwiſe) but we ought not to be ſuch Fools, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo many Tryals of them, as to believe they will ever keep Faith with us. Our Lord Jeſus indeed has taught us to forgive our Enemies, and that even in Repeated Wrongs, <hi>Luke xvii. 3. If thy Brother treſpaſs againſt thee—if he repent, forgive him.</hi> The ſame is repeated, verſ. 4. <hi>If he turn again to thee, ſaying, I repent, thou ſhalt forgive him.</hi> In which regard it would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, Whether the body of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> (I ſpeak not of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſons, but whether, I ſay, the Body of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the letter of the Evangelical Law, be ſo qualified for forgiveneſs, that we are obliged thereto. God himſelf forgives not Impenitents. But let the matter of a publick Forgiveneſs of them ſtand how it ſhall, Chriſt no where commands us to truſt our Enemies. <hi>Praying for Enemies</hi> and <hi>Truſting</hi> them, are two very different things. The former, we acknowledge our Duty, and we hope with pure Conſciences, (Hearts purged from all malice (we daily practice it to all the Enemies we have in the World: To the latter, as no Obligation can be pretended, either from Scripture or Reaſon, ſo neither can the Inveterate hatred of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> towards us be denied, or even fairly palliated. And to make it more notorious, they are now become, as one Man, ſworn Votaries to our moſt Potent Enemy, the Grand Enemy of <hi>Weſt Chriſtendum;</hi> having by this means a ſeparate Intereſt from moſt of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks of <hi>Europe;</hi> and ſo not to be truſted by us, for that very reaſon, for which we truſt divers Nations of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion. Further, what muſt make them eternally Falſe to us in any ſeeming Reconciliation, is, That as their Prieſts are the Vileſt of Men, ſo they are moſt abſolutely at the Command of their Prieſts; and perhaps no Nation under Heaven ſo much as they. And the Falſeneſs and Irreconſileableneſs of <hi>Iriſh</hi> (indeed I may ſay of any) Popiſh Prieſts to us Proteſtants, is moſt conſtant and neceſſary. For however ſundry of the Layity may be, and are, too much Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, to practice all the Conſequents of ſo Corrupt a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54544:13"/> yet as their Clergy, let all men ſay what they will, they are both Sworn to the very worſt Principles of the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith, and True to them all thoſe Ill Practices which ſuch Ill Principles draw with them.</p>
            <p>For inſtance: There is not a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſt in the World, who has not, in their Creed, as much ſworn to believe and Teach that Point,—<hi>Eccleſia Romano Catholica extra quam non eſt ſalus,</hi> (That no Perſon out of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholich Church can be ſaved) as that Chriſt Jeſus died for our Sins. And how far they practice it, in purſuance of, and agreeably to ſuch Faith, judge from that paſſage of no leſs a Man than the great Cardinal <hi>Baronius;</hi> who being to put an end to his <hi>Paraeneſis</hi> to the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> (which yet never forſook the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith, only diſobeyed the Uſurpation and pretended Laws of the Church, in puniſhing with the temporal Sword an Ecleſiaſtick Miſcreant or two) concludes, <hi>(Doleo vehementer quod abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> valete)</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">I am very ſorry I muſt end this Letter without <hi>Farewel.</hi> For <hi>ſaith he, St. John</hi> the Apoſtle, and with him all the Church, juſtly adjudgeth thoſe unworthy of Salutation, who not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, <hi>Omnis penitus ſalutis ſunt expertes)</hi> have altogether forfeited all Salvation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now from him, whom I know ſo certainly to believe me Damn'd, that he cannot in Faith or Duty allow me a <hi>Good Wiſh,</hi> I am unjuſt to my ſelf if I expect a <hi>Good Office,</hi> that is, if I truſt him: And conſequently, if I truſt any that will ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally be govern'd by him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is another Inconſiſtency for us to truſt God will Deliver us from our <hi>Irſh</hi> Popiſh Enemies, and yet to <hi>maintain them in a Capacity to hurt us.</hi> 'Tis to deſire (for truſt includes Deſire) God ſhould beſtow upon us, what we employ the moſt likely means we can to defeat. Believe it, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſt will miſchieve us as ſoon as they can, and if they are one moment innocent, 'tis (as with ſome kindred of theirs of another World) ſore againſt their Will,</p>
            <p>O let us not erre againſt our Old Error. Let us not provide that ſtill once in Thirty or Forty Years, Thirty or Forty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54544:13"/> freſh <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> muſt come over hither to find untimely Graves. Is there no Manure for the Land of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but <hi>Engliſh</hi> Blood? Do we find the Soil ſo Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile as to anſwer the Coſt of being ſo often thus fatned? Pity, ye Princes and Nobles of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ye Heads of our Tribes and Cities, as many as are here preſent; Pity your brave Countrymen; Pity your Selves; Pity your Ladies and Children; Pity your Babes which are yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born; Pity all, and ſecure all. Reſolve on effectual Counſels; Counſels and Proviſions which may bear juſt Proportion, not only to the Chriſtian Truſt which we profeſs, but to the Opportunity we now have. Never muſt we of this Age expect the like Opportunity will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to us. And if a <hi>Price be put into our Hands, and we have no heart for it,</hi> remember what Character the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt ſets on us, <hi>Prov.</hi> xvii. 16. 'Tis known, I need not name it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, It is inconſiſtent to truſt in God for Deliverance from our Enemies, (that is, for Preſervation of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt here) and to <hi>neglect the proper Means of ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</hi> Now when I ſpeak of Proper Means, I would be underſtood in a <hi>Moral Sence</hi> (for as to Politick Means, they are out of my Element:) Proper Moral Means hereto, I take to be eſpecially theſe following Vertues: <hi>Publick Spiritedneſs, Publick Sobriety,</hi> and <hi>Zeal for the true Reformed Religion;</hi> or if you pleaſe, for the truly old Religion, namely, the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> (or the Sum of the Faith in them, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed) and <hi>Holy Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to publick Spiritedneſs, <hi>Let this Mind be in you, which was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus: Look not every Man at his Own Things, but every Man alſo on the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. ii. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Things of others.</hi> And remember it is the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the worſt of Men in the latter Days, <note place="margin">2 Tim. iii. 2.</note> That they ſhould be <hi>Lovers of themſelves.</hi> Now Lovers of themſelves can never preſerve a publick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. <hi>Dum ſinguli pagnant omnes Vincuntur:</hi> Which I am
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54544:14"/> content to <hi>Engliſh, While each looks but to one, all are loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to publick Sobriety: Let each of us be careful to maintain a Serious and Conſiderative Temper; attentive to all our Concerns of Soul and Body; abandoning the Airy, Thoughtleſs, Revelling, Negligent Humour of the Age. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, leſt at any time youn hearts be over-changed with Surfieiting and Drunkenneſs.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke xxi. 34.</note> 
               <hi>Be Sober and Vigilant; your Adverſaries</hi> of all <note place="margin">1. Pet. v. 8.</note> kinds <hi>daily walk about, ſeeking to devour. Let your Loyns be girt about, and your Lights burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke xii. 35.</note> Remember the Inhabitants of <hi>Laiſh. </hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. xviii. 7.</note> 
               <hi>The People dwelt careleſs, after the manner of the</hi> Sido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, <hi>quiet and ſecure;</hi> and ſo they became an eaſie Spoil to <hi>Six hundred Danites;</hi> a Party perhaps not much more conſiderable, than ſo many of our Choice and well appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Rupperees.</p>
            <p>Finally, As to Zeal for ſimple plain Chriſtianity (for in the Appendages and Circumſtantials of it, in fine Scholaſtick improved Notions, Charity, Peace and Meekneſs becomes us, not Zeal) <hi>It is needful</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Jude,</hi> verſe 3.) <hi>to exhort you, that you earneſtly contend for the Faith once delivered to the Saints: Once,</hi> namely, by Chriſt to his Apoſtles, and by them and their Direction, now extant in Holy Scripture. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture is the True Reformed, the truly, Old Religion. And I need not tell you what Enemies the <hi>Iriſh</hi> are to your Bibles. Only give me leave to demand of the World a Reaſon, Why Chriſtian Communion ſhould not be left at that Latitude, at which Chriſt and his Apoſtles in Holy Scripture have left it? <hi>[Strictneſs in Manners,</hi> and a <hi>Scripture Latitude as to the Conditions of Church-Communion,</hi> will contribute more to the ſtrengthning the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt in this Kingdom, than all the Laws we can make without them. And being that theſe ſoon reſolve themſelves into Holineſs and Univerſal Chriſtian Charity, I muſt be bold to ſay, We ſhall not eaſily find better Preſervatives of our Church.] To this, if
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54544:14"/> Men would addict themſelves, (and why ſhould they not?) All Schiſms would ſoon be at an end.</p>
            <p>To conclude, I ſee not but theſe Vertues, duly practiced, would unite, and ſo ſecure us. In the practice then of them, Let us <hi>Truſt in that God who has delivered us from ſo great a Death; who doth deliver, and who,</hi> on theſe terms, <hi>will yet Deliver.</hi>
            </p>
            <!-- benediction -->
            <epigraph>
               <q rend="italic">And be thou, O moſt Mighty God, evermore the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation. Preſerve all its diſperſed Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies, whereſoever upon the Face of the Earth. Unite us all to fear thy Name. Purge and refine us to that degree, That we may ſhine to thy Glory, and the adorning the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
